<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: AWS | Abra&atilde;o Louren&ccedil;o]]></title>
  <link href="http://abraao.github.com/blog/categories/aws/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://abraao.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-02-05T12:22:56+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://abraao.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Abra&atilde;o Louren&ccedil;o (abraao@alourenco.com)]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[abraao@alourenco.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating a secure web proxy with an AWS EC2 instance in the Free Usage tier]]></title>
    <link href="http://abraao.github.com/blog/2012/01/29/creating-a-web-proxy-with-aws-free-usage-tier/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-29T01:19:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://abraao.github.com/blog/2012/01/29/creating-a-web-proxy-with-aws-free-usage-tier</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://aws.amazon.com/">Amazon Web Services(AWS)</a> offers a <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/free/">free usage tier</a> that includes a free Amazon EC2 Micro Instance for a year (among other benefits) to help <strong>new</strong> customers get started with the service.</p>

<h2>Limitations</h2>

<h3>Cost</h3>

<p>The <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/ec2/instance-types/">EC2 Micro Instance</a> is available for <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/free/">750 hours</a> during the year, thus it doesn't cover using the instance continuously for an entire year. Running the instance continuously for an year would cost approximately $160.20: 365 days * 24 hours - 750 hours = 8010 hours * <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/ec2/#pricing">$0.02 / hour</a> = $160.20 / year.</p>

<h3>Location</h3>

<p>The location of your proxy is limited to the regions available through EC2, which are currently <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/ec2/faqs/#Is_Amazon_EC2_running_in_more_than_one_region_When_will_EC2_be_expanding_to_new_regions">US East (Northern Virginia), US West (Oregon), US West (Northern California), EU (Ireland), Asia Pacific (Singapore), Asia Pacific (Tokyo), South America (Sao Paulo)</a>.</p>

<h3>New to AWS</h3>

<p>You must be a new customer of AWS. If you are already an AWS customer, you don't get access to the Free Usage Tier.</p>

<h3>Convenience</h3>

<p>Setting up the AWS instance is a one time setup cost, but starting and stopping it is not convenient, and may not be possible if AWS is not reachable and you didn't start the instance beforehand. The method described here could (and should) be automated.</p>

<h2>Creating an AWS account</h2>

<p>This is easy, just go to <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/">http://aws.amazon.com/</a> and sign up for an AWS account.</p>

<h2>Creating an EC2 Micro Instance</h2>

<ol>
<li>Navigate to the <a href="https://console.aws.amazon.com/ec2/">EC2 console</a>.</li>
<li>Click on "Launch Instance". <img src="/images/aws-proxy/launch-instance.png" title="Lauching an instance" ></li>
<li>Select "Quicklaunch". <img src="/images/aws-proxy/quicklaunch-aws-instance.png" title="Picking an image more quickly" ></li>
<li>Pick a meaningful name for your instance.</li>
<li>Name your key pair and download it. You'll need it later to set up key based SSH authentication against the machine. <img src="/images/aws-proxy/download-aws-keypair.png" title="Downloading AWS key pair" ></li>
<li>Select your launch configuration. e.g. Amazon Linux (64 bit).</li>
<li>Click on "Continue".</li>
<li>On the next screen, click on "Launch". <img src="images/aws-proxy/launch-new-aws-instance.png" title="Launching it for real" ></li>
</ol>


<p>Once you have your instance up and running, you can create an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SSH_tunnel#Secure_shell_tunneling">encrypted tunnel</a> through which you can transfer your browsing traffic to the instance.</p>

<h2>Using your instance as a proxy</h2>

<p>To use your instance as a proxy, you'll need to start it, get its public IP address, and establish a SSH connection to it, which we'll use to proxy traffic from your browser, instant messenger client, etc.</p>

<h3>Finding your instance's IP address</h3>

<p>Your instance will receive a new public IP every time that it's launched. To get its IP address:</p>

<ol>
<li>Log in to the <a href="https://console.aws.amazon.com/ec2/home">EC2 console</a> <img src="images/aws-proxy/ec2-console.png" title="AWS EC2 console starting screen" ></li>
<li>On the left hand navigation menu, pick <strong>Instances</strong>.</li>
<li>Select your instance. <img src="images/aws-proxy/selected-stopped-instance.png"></li>
<li>Click on "Instance Actions" and then on "Start". <img src="images/aws-proxy/starting-an-ec2-instance.png"></li>
<li>Click on "Yes, Start" on the confirmation dialog that opens.</li>
<li>Once the instance has started, select it again, and scroll the bottom part of the EC2 console until you see the <strong>Public DNS</strong> entry for your instance. This is the address you'll use to connect to your instance via SSH. <img src="images/aws-proxy/ec2-instance-public-dns.png"></li>
</ol>


<h3>Configuring a SSH client in Windows with <a href="http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/download.html">PuTTY</a></h3>

<p>To establish a connection to your instance you'll need a SSH client. For Windows platforms I recommend <a href="http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/download.html">PuTTY</a>. If you're using PuTTY, go ahead and download the installer that is labelled <strong>A Windows installer for everything except PuTTYtel</strong>. You'll need <strong>PuTTYgen</strong> (a SSH key pair generator and converter) and <strong>Pageant</strong> (an SSH authentication agent that holds your private keys in memory so you don't have to type the key password repeatedly) later on.</p>

<h4>Converting your EC2 key to PuTTY (PPK) format</h4>

<p>In order to connect to your EC2 instance with PuTTY, you'll need to convert your EC2 key pair to the PuTTY PPK format.</p>

<ol>
<li>Start PuTTYgen and select <strong>Load</strong>, then browse to your PEM file. This will automatically convert it to the PPK format. <img src="images/aws-proxy/puttygen-pem-key-converted.png"></li>
<li>Click on <strong>Save private key</strong>.</li>
<li>You can enter a passphrase if desired, but it's not necessary.

<ul>
<li>If you enter a passphrase, you'll need to input the password every time you use the key file. This can be avoided by using Pageant. <img src="images/aws-proxy/puttygen-entering-a-passphrase.png"></li>
<li>If you don't enter a passphrase (i.e. you have a blank passphrase), you won't need to enter a password every time. <img src="images/aws-proxy/puttygen-save-key-without-passphrase.png"></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>


<h4>Setting up PuTTY</h4>

<ol>
<li>Start up PuTTY, place the IP address for your instance in the text input, and set the port number to 22.</li>
<li>If you want, you can give your session a name in the <strong>Saved Sessions</strong> input box. This will allow you to save the PuTTY configuration (i.e. IP address, port number, SSH tunnel configuration). <img src="images/aws-proxy/putty-session-settings.png"></li>
<li>In the left hand navigation, expand the <strong>SSH</strong> node and click on <strong>Auth</strong>.</li>
<li>Click on <strong>Browse</strong> and select your private key file. <img src="images/aws-proxy/putty-authentication-with-private-key.png"></li>
<li>In the left hand navigation, under the <strong>SSH</strong> node, click on <strong>Tunnels</strong>.</li>
<li>Set <strong>Source port</strong> to <strong>7070</strong>, <strong>Destination</strong> to <strong>localhost</strong>, and pick <strong>Dynamic</strong> and <strong>Auto</strong>. This will set up a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SOCKS">SOCKS proxy</a> to which you can connect through port 7070 on your local computer. <img src="images/aws-proxy/putty-confuring-ssh-tunnel-socks-proxy.png"> <img src="images/aws-proxy/list-of-ssh-tunnel-socks-proxy.png"></li>
<li>On the left hand navigation, click back to <strong>Session</strong>, save your session if desired, and click on <strong>Open</strong> to start the connection to your EC2 instance.</li>
<li>When prompted for an username, enter <strong>ec2-user</strong> and press enter.</li>
</ol>


<h4>Optional: running PuTTY from a USB pen drive</h4>

<p>If you'd like to have access to your instance from any Windows computer, you can download a <a href="http://portableapps.com/apps/internet/putty_portable">portable version of PuTTY</a> to an USB pen drive and configure PuTTY as earlier in the article.</p>

<h3>Configuring a SSH client in Linux</h3>

<p>Just follow <a href="http://docs.amazonwebservices.com/AWSEC2/latest/GettingStartedGuide/ConnectToInstanceLinux.html">Amazon's instructions in the AWS documentation</a>.</p>

<h3>Configuring Firefox to use your encrypted connection</h3>

<ol>
<li>Start Firefox.</li>
<li>Click on <strong>Tools</strong>, then <strong>Options</strong>.

<ul>
<li>If you have an older version of Firefox, click on <strong>Edit</strong> then <strong>Preferences</strong>. <img src="images/aws-proxy/firefox-3.6-edit-preferences.png"></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Click on the <strong>Advanced</strong> tab, then on the <strong>Network</strong> sub-tab.</li>
<li>In the <strong>Connection</strong> area, click on the button that says <strong>Settings</strong>. <img src="images/aws-proxy/firefox-3.6-network-connection-preferences-and-settings.png"></li>
<li>On the Connection Settings screen, select <strong>Manual proxy configuration</strong>.</li>
<li>For <strong>SOCKS Host</strong>, enter <strong>localhost</strong>. For <strong>Port</strong>, enter <strong>7070</strong>. <img src="images/aws-proxy/firefox-3.6-socks-proxy-connection-settings.png"></li>
<li>Click on OK until you get back to the browser.</li>
</ol>


<p>Now the web traffic between your computer and the EC2 instance will be encrypted and you will have the IP address of the region where your EC2 instance is located.</p>

<h4>Optional: running Firefox from an USB pen drive</h4>

<p>Similarly to PuTTY, you can download a <a href="http://portableapps.com/apps/internet/firefox_portable">portable version of Firefox</a> to an USB pen drive and use it on any PC.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
