<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://abraao.github.com/blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://abraao.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-12-17T21:44:47+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://abraao.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book review: The Pragmatic Programmer]]></title>
    <link href="http://abraao.github.com/blog/2011/12/17/book-review-the-pragmatic-programmer/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-17T02:31:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://abraao.github.com/blog/2011/12/17/book-review-the-pragmatic-programmer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://pragprog.com/the-pragmatic-programmer">The Pragmatic Programmer</a> covers the activities in programming that go beyond writing code. It provides tips on how to improve the way you code by changing your process and using the right tools. Most of the items it suggests are common sense today in any software shop, but the book is still worth reading.</p>

<p>The advice in <a href="http://pragprog.com/the-pragmatic-programmer">The Pragmatic Programmer</a> is great but the technology referenced is in need of an update for the modern tech world. Who would include CVS and RCS as options for source code control systems but omit git or Mercurial?</p>

<p>The sections of the books that I liked the most were <em>The Requirements Pit</em> and <em>Pragmatic Teams</em>. In <em>The Requirements Pit</em> the authors explain how to find requirements that may be "buried beneath deep beneath layers of assumptions, misconceptions, and politics" and how to document them properly. The key point in this chapter is that "it's important to discover the underlying reason why user do a particular thing, rather than just the way they currently do it."</p>

<p><em>Pragmatic Teams</em> covers how to apply the pragmatic methods to teams:
* Teams should not tolerate broken windows.
* Someone should be in charge for guarding against scope creep or changes that weren't captured in the original agreement.
* How a team should communicate with the rest of the organization.
* Splitting teams functionally.
* Automate as much as possible.</p>

<p>One of the roles described in <em>Pragmatic Teams</em>, the project librarian, seems antiquated in a time when source code indexing and search tools are available and when good documentation is available on existing code.</p>

<p>The team that is described in <em>Pragmatic Teams</em> is a group that works together within the organization and moves from project to project together. I haven't had the opportunity to be part of such a team (i.e. teams are assembled for each project), but it's an approach that I think would be build a sense of unity between the members.</p>

<p>Overall this book is a good addition to any developer's library, but one should be careful to investigate more up to date tools.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
